<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second part to the mothers blessing: or A cure against misfortunes. Diuided into certaine principall receipts, to cure the mind of man. / By G.M..</title>
            <author>Markham, Gervase, 1568?-1637.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00417</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">57402314</idno>
  <idno type="VID">181116</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248555241</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 17387.3</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S125738</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00417)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181116)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2169:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second part to the mothers blessing: or A cure against misfortunes. Diuided into certaine principall receipts, to cure the mind of man. / By G.M..</title>
                  <author>Markham, Gervase, 1568?-1637.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 158 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.P. for Thomas Dewe, and are to be sold in S. Dunstans Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Initials.</note>
                  <note>G.M.= Gervase Markham -- Cf. STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-G¹² H⁸.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Carl H. Pforzheimer Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:181116:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:181116:1"/>
            <p>A SECOND PART TO THE Mothers Blessing: OR A CVRE AGAINST MISFORTVNES.</p>
            <p>Diuided into certaine prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall RECEIPTS, to cure the Mind of MAN.</p>
            <p>By <hi>G. M.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>G. P.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Dewe,</hi> and are to be sold in S. <hi>Dunstans</hi> Church-yard. 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:181116:2"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Cure</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Against Pouertie, and the sundry Occasions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as
<list>
                           <item>Gaming.</item>
                           <item>Robberie.</item>
                           <item>Shipwracke.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Cure</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Against casuall Losses, as
<list>
                           <item>Losse of Sight.</item>
                           <item>Losse of Children.</item>
                           <item>Losse of a Friend.</item>
                           <item>Losse of a Wife.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Cure</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> Against Contempt, and the Occasions, as
<list>
                           <item>Want of Strength.</item>
                           <item>Want of Greatnesse.</item>
                           <item>Want of Preferment.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Cure</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> Against Paine, and the Occasions, as
<list>
                           <item>Sorrow.</item>
                           <item>Torments.</item>
                           <item>Cares.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:181116:2"/>
            <head>The Preface to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN</hi> I first debated and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solued with my self to write this small Treatise, diuers obsta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles and hinderances rose vp and stood before mee, ready to take my hand from the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, as mine insufficiency in Art, and my disability to instruct others, which stand in neede my selfe of a continuall instruction; but taking a more strict Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey both of mine owne fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and other sufferance, I found me entered so farre
<pb facs="tcp:181116:3"/> within the compasse of a known and approued experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; that howsoeuer there might be rudenesse or rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in my labour; yet doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse there should not want truth nor profit. Truth, which might adorn &amp; beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie those weake Buildings, which are often shak't wi h the Stormes and Tempests of these worldly casualties; and Profit, which might inrich and support the minde, when at any time it beganne to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline or bend vnder the griping hand of that which wee call Misfortune. This expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of euils became vnto me both a spurre to set mee
<pb facs="tcp:181116:3"/> forward in that <hi>Cariere</hi> which I haue now finisht (in this little Booke:) and also an Armor to defend me against the Bitings and Bitternesse both of Curiosity &amp; Censure.</p>
            <p>A Patron or Protector to the Work I durst not assume; first, in respect I held it much too hūble for those which are both Great and Good; and next, in respect I knew it much and precious for those which are euill, proud and disdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Bookes now adayes (for the most part) come to their Patrons like Citations, from which men couet to shrinke and hide themselues; or else like Briefes, which howsoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:181116:4"/> they exhort to Charitie, yet they find few charitable: now that neither of these effects may worke vpon this, I send it thus naked into the world, and indeed would onely haue it beare it selfe, of it selfe. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dications which come from loue, many mistake, and those mistakings breed Grudgings not Gratitudes: those which proceed from desire of Gaine, are sordid and Base, and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer they may bee gilded o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, yet the poison of contempt is easie to bee tasted. Both these also I will now shunne, and onely wish them that are sicke and stand in neede, to try my Physicke; those which
<pb facs="tcp:181116:4"/> are in health and sound, may stay till disease come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them: those which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, that is, halfe sicke, halfe sound, may (if they please) try some Medicines: there is no doubt but they wil worke much, either to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, or at least to procure a preuention. I haue tryed thē, must loue them; for I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered by them. They which excercise the like, will (no doubt) find the like: they which are fearefull and dare not; or foolish and will not, let them still liue and languish; for they are neither worthy of Fathers, Mothers, no nor any good Physicians blessing.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine G. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:181116:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:181116:5"/>
            <head>A Cure against Mis-fortunes.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> A Cure against Pouertie, and the sundry occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: And first of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented pouerty.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>owsoeuer (my dearest chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren) in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of Art, which might adorne, and Authoritie, which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:181116:6"/> might defend a worke of this nature, none lesse then my selfe can lay claime to sufficiency; yet in asmuch as I know the first is sometimes but leafe gold, or an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholesome Pill, and the other, often a Veluet Gowne on a Fooles backe- Why should I staule or seeke to hide mine Ingrediens, and the rather, since in suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, and experience of worldly frailties, few e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall me. Let it suffice what I haue felt and knowne in my selfe, or seene and iudg'd in o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:181116:6"/> of that I will write freely, boldly.</p>
               <p>Nor in this will I imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the great wonder of Phylosophy, who (wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on these accidents) beganne at the top or highest part of the scale of mischiefe. But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwise, stoope to the ground and set my foot on the lowest round first, and so ascend till I come to the extreamest and last step of mortall disaster.</p>
               <p>Many will reply vnto mee, that these things (which I shall hereafter baptize by the name of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:181116:7"/> Misfortunes) are acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents not in mans pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er either to qualifie or alter; being the vnreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerable worke of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinie (which some Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>losophers would haue to be nothing else but a certaine necessity impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed vpon things, and is either caused from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, or deriued from the supposition of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples; as the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of Atomes, the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magination of the soule of the world, the order of causes, or the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Starres.) But I that know it to be a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:181116:7"/> of the Diuine Prouidence, regarding the aduentures and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uents of the inferiour life, cannot be induced to belieue, in respect it is eternall and immutable (as being in the Spirit of God) that it imposeth any necessity at all. But as it is temporall &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent (carrying her ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects into things which are humane) so she may bee said to haue power ouer the body of man, but not ouer his minde.</p>
               <p>The Starres haue no power ouer our wills, and howsoeuer the acti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:181116:8"/> of Destiny may bee necessary in the matter, in the effect it is not; but the meditation, care, wisedome and discourse which heauen may euer preuent it. So that in all the extremities of these mortall and worldly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, we haue still a refuge to flie vnto, and where our vigilance cannot, there reason and disputation with the soule may euer find out an wholesome remedy.</p>
               <p>To come then to the lowest steppe of a mans Misfortune, It is <hi>Pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> a thing so contrarie
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:181116:8"/> to an vncorrected mind (wearing on the face so foule a maske, and on the body such tatter'd garments) that where the eye can pierce no farther then the vpper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most skin of the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies; there must the minde of necessity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main torne and tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a thousand vexations. But where it is able to found the depth of these rough and disquieted waues, there shall Reason euer find safetie: and howso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the stormes or tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pests blow, yet shall hee
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:181116:9"/> either finde Sea-roome enough to auoid Rocks and shallowes, or a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour neere at hand in which hee may anchor and laugh at the windes fury.</p>
               <p>Of <hi>Pouerty</hi> there are two kindes, the one contented, the other discontented.</p>
               <p>That which wee call contented <hi>Pouerty</hi> is an honest thing, for it brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth a man to a peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and contented life, it bindeth that little hee enioyeth so fast vnto him, that <hi>Fortune</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not depriue it, and it
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:181116:9"/> makes a man liue accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Nature, not opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; It makes him know that <hi>Falsitie</hi> hath no li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, <hi>Errour,</hi> is infinite, and only <hi>Truth</hi> hath its end.</p>
               <p>This is that which is secure, for it feareth no alarmes, beates not her thoughts for escapes, nor tyers it selfe in find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out either its owne or others prouisions, whensoeuer necessitie hoysteth her sayle, the hauen lyes open stil and direct before her, there is no trouble for her en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement, no gazing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:181116:10"/> croud to pester about her, nor euer had shee need of any forraine <hi>Felicitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This labours to feed hungar (which hath a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit) not express (which is without bound) this pleaseth instant desires, not infinite longings, &amp; this possesseth things to lose them, not loseth to find them in a double worldly nature.</p>
               <p>To contemne wealth, is to draw neere vnto God, and to be content with thy chance is Dia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mond like to sparkle in the eyes of the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:181116:10"/> whilest transitory riches as a dead soyle, lies despised below it: This tels vs that Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which is grounded vpon riches is a disquiet thing; for it tormenteth it selfe, distempreth the braine, and keepes the heart continually sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. It is like the first wheele of a clocke mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing backward and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, holding a motion busie and incertaine, for it moueth some to riot, some to dissimulation, some to pride, and some to basenesse: where on the contrary part, Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:181116:11"/> which is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on contented Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, it is so absolute, that it hath no need of other Felicitie; and all things are so perfect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, that man can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire no more vnlesse it were to make it perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall.</p>
               <p>In briefe, this conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Pouertie is that which shewes vs the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable beautie of Pouertie; and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the countenance of the Poore man, with that of the Rich man, there is such alteration in complexions, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:181116:11"/> the one is all faire and louely, the other foule &amp; deformed. The Poor man that is contented▪ hath continuall smiles vpon his forehead, and laughter in his cheekes, his tongue is the instru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment to which his heart daunceth, &amp; in his eares lodge no sounds, but such as are full of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicke and sweetnes; care cannot shake him, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the tempests of the world mooue the smal lest twig of his highest branches: swifter then cloudes his troubles flie ouer, and with slower
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:181116:12"/> pace then the first Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of the spheares goes any one good thought from his bosome; where those which are For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes Minions haue no mirth but such as is fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: No pleasure, but that which weares false apparell; nor any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, but such as is guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with Distrust and Disquiet; their Pride are their torments, their preferments their fears, and their honours no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else but baites, which entice a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand mischieues to wake cōtinually about them.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:181116:12"/> They are most misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, in that sometimes they haue not liberty to bee publikely miserable, and the greatest happi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nesse in which they can boast, is that they can counterfet happinesse, though they neither taste, nor feele it.</p>
               <p>All the pompe of Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Reputation, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie and Renowne (which in mens opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are so precious, though in effect most vild and vndoing) are to these gaudy fooles no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else but false guides, which euer lead
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:181116:13"/> them from the true path of contentment; there is nothing in them wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy praise, nothing mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent, nothing to bee beloued, nor is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing in them, either to allure or entice vs more then this old foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish custome, that, <hi>Fooles doe admire them.</hi> Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth any man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll them because they are to bee desired; but because wee see many deceiued wisdomes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire them; for beleeue it all that riches is able to worke in the minde, is nothing else but an alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:181116:13"/> of opinion, an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease of Pride, a sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to Enuy, and an affection to those false shadowes of greatnesse which onely confound and consume vs.</p>
               <p>All good things ought to be without fault; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they are pure and neither corrupt nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muze the mind, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther extoll and delight it, &amp; indeed such is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented Pouertie, for it makes men confident; riches make men proud, it makes men iourney to a certaine Inne; Riches make men wander they
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:181116:14"/> know not whither; it giues greatnes of mind, Riches giues insolence; and to knit vp all, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented Pouertie is the Asse which bears Christ to <hi>Ierusalem;</hi> Riches an Imbrodred Cushion on which the Deuill sits to heare the worst of the worlds Stories. So that to bee contented with thy Pouerty, is no more to be poore, but abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly rich in all true Felicitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:181116:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> A Cure against Discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented Pouertie.</head>
               <p>DIscontented pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is a wicked and a wounding euill, for he that agreeth not with his Pouertie, may (of all men) iustly bee said to bee most vnhappy, and though hee enioy neuer so much, yet hath hee nothing but Obliquie and Discontent, as his best and dearest compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. For what auayles it a man to bee master of both the <hi>Indies,</hi> if not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:181116:15"/> his long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings bee fixt vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther mans fortunes, if those things cannot please him which are gotten, but still his thirst rangeth after things new to be attayned; how rich or poore soeuer his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be, how emptie or full his Barnes; how fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite or infinite his Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; how small his debts, or great his vsury, yet is this man said to be poor, in the worst and most vnwholsomest construc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>This man making him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe a slaue to his owne
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:181116:15"/> opinion, is becom'd a slaue to all wise mens iudgements; for hee is wretched that iudgeth not himselfe to bee most blessed, neither can hee be happy, whose owne heart is a continuall trumpet to clamor his owne misfortunes.</p>
               <p>Simple Pouertie in it selfe (when it assaults a man) comes silently, peaceably, like a gentle calme, and neither af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>frights the Eyes with horrible apparitions, nor the Eares with dreadfull sounds. It hath neither flashes of lightning to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:181116:16"/> dazell vs, nor claps of Thunder to amaze vs. But when it is vsher'd forth with Discontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then it appeares in the most dreadfullest pompe that may be, then Fire, Sword, Famine, Boults, Bonds, &amp; whole Armies of wilde Beasts muster about it, and with a greedinesse more insa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate then death seed and deuoure both our liues and Intrailes. It then sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesteth euils, not proues them, shewes vs feares to weaken courage, not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame it; and (like the Diuell) conuayes vs to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:181116:16"/> a high Mountain, where it shewes vs the whole world for a temptation, not a blessing.</p>
               <p>Besides, discontented Pouertie neuer walketh without two malicious Fiends in his company, Enuy and Couetousnes, the one fills his mouth with disparagements at others prosperities, the other cloyes his heart with continuall new de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires of those things which are still either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue or beyond him; and as the malice of the first makes him hate the person, but admire the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:181116:17"/> condition which is plac't in a Spheare to exceed him; so the infinite long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the latter shewes him such instabilitie and incertaintie both in the attaining and holding of those riches, for which hee had formerly sold and abiured all whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some contentment; that being made a slaue to discontent and desire, there is no estate of any creature which can bee more vilde or despised.</p>
               <p>So that hence, this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion must needes bee gathered, That as the man which hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:181116:17"/> but what nature simply desireth, is simply accounted poore, or sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply miserable: So hee which is vtterly discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with his estate, and only becomes the seruant of opinion; that man is truely most poore, truely most miserable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> A Cure against all Pouertie in Generall.</head>
               <p>HAuing thus taken a suruay of these two contrary pictures, and (as it were) in two Bundels
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:181116:18"/> knit vp their defects and perfections, let mee not blunt my Pen with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasions touching either the one or the others e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, for no mind can bee so sottish as not easily to iudge of these colours. Remember they are su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities which we sweat and labour for; things na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and necessary God hath prouided in a plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full manner. Seest thou the springs &amp; watry veines of the earth, what thirst will they not quench? Seest thou the surface and couering of the ground, what hunger will it not
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:181116:18"/> stanch? Seest thou the Beasts of the Field, whom will they not cloath? And seest thou not the Trees of the Forrest? whom will they not shade and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend from tempests. As for things of contrary na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as Gold, Mynerals, Pearles, Precious stones, (which howsoeuer wee long or labour for, yet (many times) they are found burthensome and wounding to those which possesse them;) these hath prouident Nature either lockt vp in the Earth, or hidden in the Seas, as things which being bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:181116:19"/> vp or wrested from their closets (by our pains and industries) rather threaten vs with iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, then fill vs with comforts.</p>
               <p>The measure which we should hold in our desires, is to haue all things neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, things sufficient, and he which strayeth beyond that bound, falleth into a <hi>Precipis,</hi> whence there is no recouery from the present ruine of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments; for Nature al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes vs but onely this, Not to bee hungry, not to be thirstie, not to be cold; and for these things wee
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:181116:19"/> neither need to sweat, nor yet to weare out our appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell. Our cares need not make vs old, nor our at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts draw vpon vs the hate either of our home or forraine neighbours.</p>
               <p>Pouerty is no hindrance to any good action; It is only the ambitious desire of wealth which brings vpon vs, and makes vs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with euery disa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster. What thiefe will bid a poor man stand? or what malice will shoot his darts against that bosome which is arm'd with a confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that is able to break or returne them backe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:181116:20"/> the face of the shooter.</p>
               <p>Since then Pouertie is so good, so wholsome, so secure, since it keepes the body in firme health, and clenseth the minde of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry turbulent and vnruly passion, why should wee shrinke, or out of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlines of our deceiued natures start from it as a bug-beare. No let vs ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with open armes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, kisse, and imbrace it. Nay howsoeuer wee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in the goods of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; what admirations soeuer depend or cluster about vs; what Honours soeuer cloath vs, what
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:181116:20"/> Fauours soeuer supports vs, though the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quers of Kings lay open to vs; be our garments steele, scarlet, or purple; yet the very imitation of Pouerty is excellent and pleasant. And a man shall be made more assuredly rich, when hee knowes it is neither painefull nor grieuous, at any time to bee made poore.</p>
               <p>It is our inacquaintance with Pouertie which makes vs feare Pouertie, and those which tell vs the strange tales of its hidde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse and deformitie; deale with vs as the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:181116:21"/> did both with vs and other Nations in their first conquest of the West Indies: make the Sauages beleeue that (all but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues) were Men-eaters, cruel, and without mercy; so that they fled from all other commercement; but experience brought forth other proofes. And in like manner of Pouertie, hee that least knowes it, most feares it. But he that with <hi>Lucillius</hi> will take <hi>Senecaes</hi> counsell, and at least once a moneth truely and seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously enter into a strong and perfect imitation, shal bee assured neuer after to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:181116:21"/> feare it; for it is as easie to indure Pouertie alwayes, as to attempt it once. And for a further testimony, euen <hi>Epicurus</hi> himselfe (to whom the very sound of Pouertie was (like the shrikes of Mandrakes, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and killing) boasted in an Epistle he writ to <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinus,</hi> that hee had found more true contentment in one moneths imitation of Pouertie, then in all the pleasures, feasts, &amp; riches which he had either seene or possest in the whole circuite of his life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>But why striue I thus to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:181116:22"/> make the world in loue with Pouertie; thinke you it is because I would draw all men either to the dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>station, or from the posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of honest riches: No, God forbid, let euery man enioy his goods free<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, securely; yet by all meanes without feare; so loue them, as they may serue thee, not command thee: imbrace them as guesse which thou canst kindly entertaine for a night, and with as much friendship againe shake hands and depart with thee next morning; think them not houshold Gods, but
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:181116:22"/> transsitorie gifts: for, <hi>Few dye rich, lesse liue rich, and none were euer borne rich.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thou mayest imploy them for thine occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but not admire them for their counsels: for beleeue it nothing is fuller of flattery, nothing fuller of falshood. Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches wil say this man fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth thee, or this man loueth thee, when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is but something in thee: whereas Pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is euer honest, true and full of plain dealing. It wil point thee out, and shew thee the very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:181116:23"/> charracter of those which are thine vnfained friends, of such as loue thee for thy selfe, not for thy fortunes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore howsoeuer Riches may haue thy counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance or imployment, yet is Pouertie onely worthy of thy sincere loue and affection.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> A Cure against losse of Wealth, by Gaming, Ryot, &amp;c. being an occasion of Pouertie.</head>
               <p>SOm will say vnto me, that the effects which
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:181116:23"/> spring from Pouertie, may be easie and porta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but the cause heauy and intollerable. As that thou hast spent thy wealth and substance in gaming, riot, or those disorderly and vnruely courses, which like a <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> catching hold vpon the wills of men, instant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly transformes them into all the shapes of <hi>Dis-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</hi> Let this bee granted, and that gaming or the like hath consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med thee: Alas, what hast thou lost? Mony, Lands, Reuenues; things par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture would haue
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:181116:24"/> lost thee, for who knows the euills which might haue sprung, either from too much loue, too little care, or too vilde an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. Thou hast lost but what thou hadst, nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther hast thou done any miracle or strange thing; but onely shewed thy selfe somwhat too grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to Fortune, in resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring backe to her all that in an instant, which par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture she had beene many ages in bestowing. This may be an act of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>discretion &amp; so worthy repentance, not despaire, or the mindes infinite
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:181116:24"/> disturbance. These losses <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re many times the losse of greater dangers, and when folly &amp; guilt haue thus brought thee to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, thou maist then comfort thy selfe with this assurance, that so long as thou keep'st Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome either for thy friend or companion, so long it will defend thee from any relapse or se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond falling into the same mischiefe.</p>
               <p>Hast thou (at game) lost thy wealth, lose with it also thy couetousnes, then hast thou made thy selfe most happily hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:181116:25"/> for in parting with a white <hi>Witch,</hi> thou hast also forsaken a black <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uill,</hi> and though thou took'st a wrong way for thy deliuerance, yet whē thou shalt, (tyred, torne, and wounded) find out the harbour of conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Pouerty, thou shalt there in the quiet calme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of thy meditations find a readie and soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne balme for the cure of all thy mischiefs. But if thy mind (like <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zentius</hi>) will still keepe thy liuing couetousnesse bound to thy dead for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes; yet shalt thou find
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:181116:25"/> this happines in thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer vnhappie losses, that it hath left thee neither Wood nor Oyle, Flint, Tinder, nor Steele to strike on, whereby euer againe either to kindle, feed, or nourish a fire so horrible, dreadfull, and consuming.</p>
               <p>Againe, is thy wealth lost by game or the like bewitching inticements; O but consider how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (as well as thy selfe) may be poisoned by this change or transmutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Thinke of the infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it carrieth with it, how catching it is and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:181116:26"/> how destroying: Thinke of thy false baites, how sweet they are, yet poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonous and deceiuing, and thinke of the ends to which it endeuours to draw all mortall opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; thou shalt find in them nothing but vaine glory, pride, and ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: this consideration shall make thee walke lightly vpon the ground and hauing (as it were) disburden thee of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>supportable load; thou shalt find thy selfe light and nimble to runne the race of any noble and praise-woorthy action:
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:181116:26"/> Neither the suruey of Houses, the proofe of Oxen, nor the intice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a wife, shall bee able to detaine thee one minute from following that guide, which shall conduct thee to all true felicitie: Thou shalt now liue secure in thine owne cottage, &amp; neither haue Heire to languish at the prosperity of thy health, nor doubt an Heire, whose couetousnes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, or riot, may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken thy dead bones from the graue, &amp; make thee (as it were) liue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in the shame of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:181116:27"/> their wicked courses. Fortune in this case is become thy Physitian, not thy disease, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all lamentation, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry, or complaining, is sencelesse and without reason.</p>
               <p>Remember it is thy selfe, which thy selfe woundest, for hadst thou kept them like Nose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayes, whereat to smell for a day, and then to cast off and neglect the next morning, being wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and without sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour; there could haue bin no cause of torment, no cause of complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:181116:27"/> Remember thou hast lost nothing but what another had lost before; (for the gifts of Fortune spring not newe, but grow from Succession) nothing thou hast but what an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other had, nor any thing hast thou lost, but what thou mayst imagine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, to the ende (for a while) thou mightest enioy them.</p>
               <p>Thinke of the Phylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers Cobler which lost his singing when hee found his wealth, and thinke of the wholesom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of the Purgation
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:181116:28"/> thou hast taken, which hath disburthened thee of that which hath dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned so many. Be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full therefore hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth not of thy losse of money, but of thy losse of time, nor complaine for the iniuries done thee by Fortune, but the abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses done by thy selfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Gods creatures; so shall thy sinne, and not thy wealth, grieue thee: and when thou hast wrought in thy selfe a noble reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thou shalt finde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment gather about thee; neither shall thy
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:181116:28"/> Mother (like the Spanish Lady) coniure thee from playing away her cloathes before her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die receiue buriall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> A Cure against Robbery, or Stealth, being an occasion of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie.</head>
               <p>BVt it is not game which is thine afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; thou hast fallne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of thieues, and so art robd &amp; spoyld of all thou enioyedst: doubtlesse this is grie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uous
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:181116:29"/> at the first appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension, but when thou shalt (with a premeditate iudgement) compare it with other mens misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, it wil then appeare light, gentle, and easie, for thou hast falne into the hands of thieues who haue rob'd thee of the goods of Fortune, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man hath falne into the hands of thieues, and they haue taken from him both life &amp; fortune.</p>
               <p>Thou hast falne into the hands of thieues, and they haue taken from thee a little momentarie wealth, another man
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:181116:29"/> hath falne into the hands of slanderers and detrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and haue taken from him the euerlasting por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his good name and reputation; euer that reputation which is so delicate and pure, that the least excesse doth spot it, any thing that is vniust, doth it dishonor: but all things which taste either of Folly, Sloath, or Rashnesse, they ruine it for euer. That without the which man is farre worse then a beast; &amp; that, which so long as it abides and is his gentle companion;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:181116:30"/> hee liues as an Angell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst men full of loue, and full of braue admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               <p>Thou hast falne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of thieues, and they haue taken from thee a Bundle of necessaries, which might haue adorned and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified thy Bodie. But another man hath falne into the hands of Coze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and they haue cheated him of all the benefits and blessings of his mind; for they haue turn'd his discretion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to folly, his iudgement into rashnesse, his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:181116:30"/> into furie, and made his heart a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace meete to entertaine nothing but flattery and dissimulation.</p>
               <p>VVhat Traueller is hee which knowes not the daunger of High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes? and what fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cast is that which can shake hands with VVise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and is not armed either with Strength to withstand, or else with Patience to entertaine the worst of these casuall misaduentures.</p>
               <p>But thou mourn'st, thou complayn'st, nay thou art halfe madde, for
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:181116:31"/> these crosses and losses, when in truth thou oughtest rather to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph and reioyce that thou hast escapt bonds, wounds, nay death it selfe; all which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly are adiuncts to these mischiefes. What knowest thou whether heauen thought thy goods a meeter venome to impoyson him that stole them, then thee which truly possessedst them; doubtlesse it is that <hi>Prouidence</hi> hath an eye into all these thy proceedings, and when soeuer thy passionate
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:181116:31"/> griefe shal make thee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell thereat, thou hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest to thy selfe a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vexation.</p>
               <p>But thou hast not falne into the handes of Theeues onely; but Theeues &amp; dissemblers, which were thy knowne and professed enemies, heere is a newe distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance fallne vnto thee, yet in this rather blame thy selfe then thy For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; for looke with what euer Armour thou wouldest encounter a Wolfe (as thou passest ouer the Alpes) or with what shield thou
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:181116:32"/> wouldest receiue the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sault of an inuenomed Serpent, with the like care and strength thou shouldst euer prouide thy selfe of succours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all the attempts of thy knowne Enemies. Haue euer a power to repulse them, or else a scorne that can represse them. But where those two faile, there call a Wisedome full of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience vnto thee, and let it either make thee gracious in their eyes (which is the best and most assured conquest) or else let it strengthen
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:181116:32"/> thy minde and resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that these tryalls shall make thee fitter for God, being taken as wholesome plaisters for thy soule) and thine enemies fitter for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and infamy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whips and spurres to bring them furious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:181116:33"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> A Cure against Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke, being an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of Pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</head>
               <p>YEt it is not this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of vndoing, all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready rehearsed, which maks thee repine against thy Pouertie; but thou hast now suffered Shpp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke, and therein per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture not onely lost thine owne, but the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state of those which put trust and confidence in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:181116:33"/> thee, and if this be not worthy thy teares, Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row hath none, Reason findes none.</p>
               <p>But doe not deceiue thy selfe for of all casu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties this is the easiest, and hee which for this shall runne into dispaire, sinnes not onely against himselfe, but against him that is the Tamer and Ruler of Tempests; and therefore if thou hast suffered Shipwrack, thinke not of what thou hast lost (for that is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recouerable) but of what thou hast escaped, (for to it belongs both
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:181116:34"/> thy praise and thankes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing) thinke not of the raging and violence of the Stormes, or swelling of the Seas, but thinke of thy hidden sinnes and transgressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which might call vp these Windes to striue and combate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thee.</p>
               <p>I, but still the horror is before thine eyes, nor can the memory of the danger bee taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from thy cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; The darkenesse of the day, the amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lightening, the dreadfulnesse of the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:181116:34"/> Thunder, the clamour of the Windes, the cries of the people, the cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Seas, &amp; the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit contention betwixt life, death, hope, despaire and desolation like so many massie hammers lye continually beating vpon thy heart, with a fresh remembrance of thy forepassed troubles; yet all this is but weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and a Feather thrust into the ballance, against a Mountaine. When thou shalt call into thy minde who it was that spake vnto thee in this dreadfull and powerfull
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:181116:35"/> manner. Not a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard vpon the Rockes but hath seene the like, not a Fisherman but knowes the like, and many Pylgrimes of the Seas haue felt the like. It is no newe thing, for it hath beene in all ages: It is no strange thing, for euery day (almost) brings foorth the like accident, and it is no euill thing, for it brings man to the knowledge of his owne sinne, and to the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of Gods infinite mercy and power.</p>
               <p>But thou cammest na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to the Shoare, Sea-beaten,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:181116:35"/> bruised, sicke, and halfe drowned; yet thou diddst attaine land, and recouered. O heere is a comfort farre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond al thy calamity, for what art thou, or what canst thou assume, that thus thou shouldest find a particular and an espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall preseruation.</p>
               <p>But yet thou hast lost all thy goods, all thine estate, and all (that in this world) thou diddst make account should support thee; why let them goe, who knowes but they were a debt thy sinnes did owe vnto the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:181116:36"/> Seas. And if by the law of Nations wee are bound to pay that which we borrow: what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly would grieue at this restitution, and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther since it is calld vpon by him who is the len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, giuer, and disposer of all things. Triumphe at the losse of these Goods, and with them lose thy vices, so shall thy ioyes be perfect.</p>
               <p>Take vnto thee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented pouertie, and with it liue freely, se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely. And for a bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fillet to knit vp all that hath already
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:181116:36"/> beene spoken, take this lesson from the worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est of all Phylosophers, (the Morall <hi>Seneca) That there is no good whatsoeuer, profitable to him which possesseth it, except that which hee is euer addressed to lose with his most willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:181116:37"/>
            <head>The Second Receit.</head>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> A Cure against Casuall Losses; and first of losse of Sight.</head>
               <p>THE casuall losses which happen to man, and doe disturbe, distract, and afright the mind, are of two kindes, the one Externall, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Internall; of Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall casualties none are more pernicious and hurtfull, then those
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:181116:37"/> which happen to the Senses: As to lose <hi>Smel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Tasting,</hi> or <hi>Feeling,</hi> are accidents most dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleasant: To lose the <hi>hearing</hi> most dangerous; but to lose the Sight most grieuous. As for the losse of Member, custome (commonly) takes away the care, and Art findes a supply by which (many times) the defect is hidden. Since then the bent of this dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course leuelleth onely how to correct the mind of this vnreasonable sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, I will heere vnder this one head, of <hi>The
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:181116:38"/> Losse of Sight,</hi> compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend all other externall casualties whatsoeuer.</p>
               <p>It is true that thou hast lost thy sight, and thou grieuest past mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, past mitigation; for which thou hast bidden the whole world good night, and shalt no more behold the faire glory of the skie, the brightnesse of the Sunne, the belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued complexions of thy friends, nor the desired beauties of thy dearest wife and children. Thy Feete haue lost their guide; thy Hands their Tutor, and thy mind its
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:181116:38"/> Election. Thou art now no more thy selfe, but Infant-like runnest back into thy Cradle, and art (in all thy outward ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) to bee ruled and gouerned by the Foster nurses commandement.</p>
               <p>O let not thy griefe thus deceiue thee, but call vp into thy minde thoughts of a better composition: Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Philosophy teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs, that, <hi>Bodily blindnesse is a part of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence,</hi> and that night and obscuritie haue their pleasures as well as the day and sun-shine:
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:181116:39"/> Thou hast not lost thy sight, but return'd it backe from thine eyes to thy soule; drawne it from a weake Garrison, which euerye vanitie could surprise, to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible Fort, which no worldly illusion can or ought to conquer. Thou hast by this losse, brought to thy soule this benefit. A much abler iudgement, a more stayed Memorie, and a most absolute Diuine Meditation. Thou hast in this losse, lost milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Desires, euerie one more dangerous
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:181116:39"/> and more killing to thy Soule, then a generall plague to an infected Armie, for the Eye is the vniuersall and hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Baud which allures and inticeth vs to all manner of sinnes that are mortall. The Eye shewed <hi>Comodus</hi> his lust, <hi>Caligula</hi> his incest, and taught <hi>Tarquine</hi> the way to rauishment. It was the Eye (seeing the honour done vnto the gods) which stir'd the pride in <hi>Clearchus</hi> the Tyrant, that hee call'd himselfe <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and tooke vpon him the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:181116:40"/> practise or artificiall Lightening and Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. It was the Eye that made <hi>Alexander</hi> enuy the conquests of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Philip:</hi> the Eye made <hi>Heliogabalus</hi> so nice, slothfull, and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate, that he forsooke all manly attributes, and wisht no other death, but to be smoothered in Roses. The Eye made <hi>Caesar</hi> couetous of a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy: the Eye made <hi>Nero</hi> digge into the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trailes of his owne Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to please the Eye, <hi>Anthony</hi> had the wealth of a rich Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:181116:40"/> lauishly spent at one Feast, for his most vnfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate entertainement.</p>
               <p>Of what sinne is not the Eye guiltie, what mischiefe doth it not pursue, and what vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie doth it not hold ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in act or imitation? There is no fashion so hatefull, vild and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but if the Eye see it, the Body presently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaines it; no beautie so chaste, pure, or innocent, but if the Eye behold it, the heart instantly is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed; nor is there any vanity (of what conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on soeuer) but still there
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:181116:41"/> is some Eye that will both loue and admire it. O how happy art thou then, that by thy depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation art depriued of these mischiefes; Nay, wouldst thou but silently sit &amp; call into thy memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a Catalogue of those obiects which thou hast lost, and which rather thē thou wouldst behold thou wouldst teare thine eyes from their Coffins; euen that recordation would giue thee such cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, that al thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer griefes (like withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red leaues) would fall from their branches.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:181116:41"/>
               <p>To conclude, the Eye is the weapon and sting of vices, and the guide or vsher, which goes before, and leades vs the way to all sinne and wickednesse: if then to haue this wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon put into Vertues hand, and this Guide set in so faire &amp; euen a path, that he cannot stray from a pious meditation: if this be a blessing, thou art blest in thy losses; and howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thine eyes want out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward light, yet shall thy soule be inriched with the multiplications of a world of other glories.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:181116:42"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 8.</hi> A Cure against the losse of Children.</head>
               <p>MEe thinkes, I heare thee complaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee, that it is not any externall losse, (of which I haue spoken) that afflicts thee, but thou hast an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall and greater disaster within thee: thou hast lost thy children; and that losse hath reason to teare vp and wound thine intrailes within thee: thy blood is distempered, nature vext, and the whole frame both of thy body and mind put quite out of order: to this
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:181116:42"/> sorrow there is no mitiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, neither canst thou be comforted, because they are not.</p>
               <p>Bee not deceiued with this Sophistry of nature, and thine owne opinion; let not thy particular affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction draw thee into a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall absurditie: for there is not a greater folly moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, then too much, or too vnseasonably to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayle the death of those which are mortall: why, they brought no certainty into the world but this, that they must die; neither can they carry any greater glory hence, or more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:181116:43"/> then this, that they are dead with faire and honest reputation.</p>
               <p>But thy children are lost; alas, this is no new thing, no strange thing, no euill thing: no new thing; for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Family, Commerce, and society are subiect and lyable to the same acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: wheresoeuer man doth soiourne, there hath death euer his habitation; and from the beginning of the world, all that haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken breath, haue likewise died: it is no strange thing; for the first father liued to suruiue his best sonne; nay, liued to see him slaine; nay,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:181116:43"/> slaine most vnnaturally; slaine by his owne brother: and it is no euill thing; for it is but a payment of that debt, for which wee had contracted with nature, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer since the first man was shut out of Paradise: it is our manumission or free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from the flesh, the world, and her deceitfull allurements; and it is the Port or Gate, thorow which onely, and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we haue our passage to eternall felicitie, and shall come to behold the most glorious face of our Maker.</p>
               <p>But thou wouldst haue
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:181116:44"/> had thy children to haue suruiued thee, that the comfort of their successi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on might haue giuen to thy name a kind of eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; which lost and preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, thou accountest thy self vndone and wretched: why consider? doth any man call a tree miserable, because she sheds her fruit on the ground, whilst her branches flourish and mount vpward? doth any man account the <hi>Storke</hi> vnnaturall, because shee casts downe one of her young ones, to pay the rent for her protection? In like case, thy childrē are thy
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:181116:44"/> fruit, and whether they fall late or early, it is without thy disparagement; they are thy rent, and whensoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thou payest them, it is not before they are due; for to thy omnipotent Landlord thou art euer a debtor.</p>
               <p>Againe, no man is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from these strokes: Death is a free visitor, and whensoeuer he thrusts his Sheare into the corne, the haruest is alwaies ripe and ready: vntimely burials come as well out of the Cottage, as the Capitoll: no man hath priuiledge; for when the poorest Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:181116:45"/> mourned for the losse of his first-born, euen <hi>Pharaoh</hi> himselfe (in the same hower) was toucht with the like lamentation. Destiny and Old-age differ much in their progresse; for they neuer keepe one and the same order, but as the one hath an assurance and certainty not to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded, and so walkes slowly: so the other, being euermore at the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement and disposition of <hi>Prouidence,</hi> is euer swift, watchfull, sudden, and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious.</p>
               <p>No man goes out of the world at the same Port
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:181116:45"/> which he entred, but as they wander seueral waies, so they find seuerall paths to conduct them to that Rest, which is, and must euer be howerly expected, Why doest thou then tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and afflict thy selfe for the losse of thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren? or what in that acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath happened vnto thee contrary to thy hope? questionlesse nothing: for those which were borne to die, are dead, not any in whom there was a hope (in this world) to be eternall: nay, those which ought to die, are dead; and will any wisedome murmure at the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:181116:46"/> discharge of so honest and so expected a duty.</p>
               <p>But it is contrary to thy wish; for thou wouldst still haue enioyed them, still haue fed vpon the sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of their loued Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: but did any promise vnto thee such a feast? is it possible to find such a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? or can earth chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge so much as the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of such a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract? O no, fie no, the dayes of life are numbred, and it is impossible for any sorrow or perplexitie in man to adde or diminish the smallest part of the smallest minute or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:181116:46"/> of Time.</p>
               <p>But yet thy children are lost, and this impostume cannot so soone be either broken or healed; they were thy flesh, and in their death thou hast receiued a wound both aking and smarting: if it be so, call to thy consideration who hath them; and then argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his and thine owne ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, at the Barre of Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencie, and before the face of an vnpartiall Iudgment, thou shalt finde, that hee which holds them, was the certaine, true, and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting Owner, and thy selfe but a poore borrower, that
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:181116:47"/> in thy returne, hast hardly sent backe the halfe part of the Moitie. They were lent thee onely to bring vp, onely to informe in all Christian duties: this if thou hast fulfilled, thou hast discharged the part of a good parent, and they returne backe to their true and perfect owner with more glorie, and a much better acceptation: here is cause of reioycing, not of mourning.</p>
               <p>Yet for all this they are dead, and in their death thou hast lost all thy fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hopes, all thy sweet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations; thou shalt not
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:181116:47"/> now see one of them rais'd to the highest scale of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; a second sit in Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, and a third armed in Steele, bring forraine Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs home into his own Citie. O doe not deceiue thy goodnes with these in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainties! this losse or change hath brought thee a much better assurance, thou needest not now hope, but maist with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence say to thine owne soule, that thou hast seene the vttermost worst which the malice of <hi>Enuy</hi> or <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune</hi> can possibly worke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them. Thou shalt not henceforth neede to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:181116:48"/> feare this childs ambition, that's Couetousnesse, nor the others Ryot; thou shalt not see one keep a market for <hi>Honor;</hi> another a Sham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles for Bloud; nor the third a <hi>Seralia,</hi> for varietie of all manner of Concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scence. Thou shalt not see them mount to dignity by Bribes; afterwards pawne it to Couetousnes, and in the end forfeit all to the Gallowes: neither shalt thou see them depart out of the world, one with Infamie; another with Curses; and a third with diseases. Of these feares thou art releast, and thou
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:181116:48"/> maist with a sweet comfort informe thy selfe, that when next thou shalt meet them in the higher Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, thou shalt then see thē cloathed in white gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and crowned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the Angels. If this aske teares, ioy hath no dwelling; neither is there left vpon the earth (for a pyous delight) either har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour or habitation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:181116:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 9.</hi> A Cure against the losse of a Friend.</head>
               <p>BVt all these losses (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid) are remoued, and thou hast now a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and much heauier weight within thee, <hi>Thou hast lost thy Friend,</hi> thy faithfull friend, thy true friend, the companion of thy comforts, the closset of thy counsels, and the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sicion to all thy cares and afflictions; thou hast lost him that liued in thee, and thou in him; one that by an equall sympathy of sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:181116:49"/> and delight, partake with thee in all things, of what nature and condition so euer.</p>
               <p>This then &amp; thy sorrow approues that thou hadst a Friend, &amp; neither was the roughnesse of thy, nature, nor the inciuilitie of thy conuersation so barbarous or stupid, that thou couldst neither affect, nor yet bee affected; thou had'st in thee some sweetnesse; some goodnes: sweetnesse to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure, and goodnes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and pay this obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of friendship.</p>
               <p>But thou hast lost thy Friend. No, the delight of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:181116:50"/> his memory will euer be a liuing companion within thee; neither must thou imagine him lost, but reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: That he is iourneyed vpon so important, so ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarie, and so laudable an occasion, as his honour and renowne stood enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, in the dispatch of so noble and predestinate an errand. And to repine in thy teares at this worke of necessitie, were to discouer in thee an affection, but no true or faithfull friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship. Should the King im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy him vpon an honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Negotiation to the furthest <hi>Indies,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:181116:50"/> the rage of the Seas, the danger of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pests, the infection of the Lyne, and the barbarous cruelty of sauage Nations; yet wouldst thou not only animate, but second his voyage both with thy vowes and wishes. And now the King of Heauen hath call'd him vp to bee a <hi>Ledgier</hi> for euer in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall <hi>Ierusalem:</hi> Wilt thou mourne and wring thy hands, as if he went to the Scaffold or Gibbet? this were to doe him a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracefull courtesie: and as <hi>Fabius Verrucosus</hi> cals it, to feede thy best friend with
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:181116:51"/> a white Loafe of grauelly Bread.</p>
               <p>But thy friend is lost, I lost for euer, thou shalt no more enioy the flowers of his friendship, the delight of his discourse, nor the comfort of his Societie. Was he then so excellent? so perfect? so absolute? had hee that Triumuerat of qualities within him, which makes vp an exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site and complete man? Was he Religious? was he honest? was he valiant? Then make him thy Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie: make him thy Presi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, &amp; by his Character, and no other, modell out
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:181116:51"/> and frame for thy selfe a second election. But if this proue difficult, and that thy curiositie wants either <hi>Patience</hi> to indure the choyce, or that thy heart (being closed vp) will not suffer thy iudgement to entertain a second change: Then take <hi>Seneca's</hi> aduice, and search into the Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Sciences; into the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest &amp; vndeceiuing trades of the vpright Artificers; or into the laudable exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cises of militarie and ciuill professions, and there seek thee out a companion which can neuer remoue, till first thy selfe be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:181116:52"/> This benefit is not found out in crowdes, it comes not at the Court, it cares not for the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, neither takes it delight either in Feasts or Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs. This friend thou shalt finde frugall for thine estate: honest, for thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersation; and wholesome to aduise thee in all the perplexities of Fortune.</p>
               <p>But hast thou lost thy friend, thy one and onely friend: Hadst thou then but one? O blush for shame, that hauing liued til thou beest able to iudge of a friend, thou canst yet boast the losse but of one
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:181116:52"/> man onely. How many <hi>Catoes?</hi> how many of the <hi>Lelij?</hi> how many <hi>Scipio's?</hi> how many <hi>Cicero's</hi> yearely depart this world, and yet in all their losse thou find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est no interest? Question<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse thou hast either been too curious and nice in thine election, or else much by much too im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouident, that sayling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the stormes and gusts of this world, thou wouldst trust thy poore Barke to hold but by one Anchor (and no more) in so great a tempest.</p>
               <p>Thou hast lost thy friend: No, he is but chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:181116:53"/> to a much better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: he was before but thy friend made of earth; he is now thy friend com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed of a Diuine and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall substance: Hee was before an example for thy body (how thou mightest liue well;) he is now a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sident for thy soule (how thou mayst dye to liue for euer well:) He was before thy comfort, let him now be thine admiration. If this be a cause of teares, then where is our reioysing? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, <hi>Destinie</hi> sends no man out of this world, nor lets any man liue in this world, without some
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:181116:53"/> stroke: And poore is that wisedome, whose expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not armed with <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> euer to encounter with that assault and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate.</p>
               <p>These afflictions truely considered, are Tributes, not Torments, &amp; nothing alters either the nature or complexion, but an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefull acceptation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 10.</hi> A Cure against the losse of a Wife.</head>
               <p>DOubtlesse this Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophy (like a gentle
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:181116:54"/> Lenitiue) might supple and mollifie the agonies before shewed. But now a much greater torrent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerflowes thee, <hi>Thou hast lost thy Wife,</hi> selfe of thy self, flesh of thy flesh, thine owne and onely dearest companion: Shee that is the Cabenet in which thou hast lockt vp thy Vowes; the roote out of which thou dost deriue all thy goodly Branches; the honour of thy bed, and the crowne by which thou shalt be held in reuerence to all after posteritie. Nay, thou hast lost a good wife; if this deserue not teares,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:181116:54"/> then for euer hereafter let affliction no more bee named.</p>
               <p>I pray thee let me (with the Philosopher) aske thee thus question: Didst thou finde her good? or make her good? wert thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to Chance or Art; If to the first (beleeue it) that shop of Nature is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer empty: and though a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst many parcels there bee much frayd, sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed and stained ware; yet is there still enough that is excellent and rich, and as able as the first to adorne thee. If to the latter thou be a debtor; what folly is in
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:181116:55"/> thee either to mourne or despaire? for though the patterne bee lost, yet thy selfe and thine Art surui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and from the like quantity thou maist euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more fashion the like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions; 'tis but one and the same labour: and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse industry tyre, hardly can the worke runne out of Compasse.</p>
               <p>But thou hast lost a good Wife. Tell me? into how many links was that chaine of Goodnesse diuided? Thou wilt answer me▪ She was <hi>Chaste;</hi> so was <hi>Drusilla</hi> till <hi>Caius</hi> (her owne bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) turned her to a
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:181116:55"/> Strumpet; so was <hi>Poppea,</hi> till extreme couetousnesse bewitcht her; and so was <hi>Paulina,</hi> till the vowes and oathes of a <hi>Cardinall</hi> sent all vertue beyond her. O do but reade the Romane Stories, and you shall see how many chaste Matrons <hi>Clodius</hi> seduced; and how many that had liued long with their Husbands in rare Reputation, fell at last by the lust of <hi>Scaurus Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercus,</hi> and sold their Fames ouer to disgrace and Folly: to which iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, early-death is euer a preuention.</p>
               <p>But thine was modest:
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:181116:56"/> So no doubt was <hi>Xantippe,</hi> till pride and <hi>Socrates</hi> suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance taught her to vse and imploy an audacious conquest; and so no doubt was the mother of <hi>Paupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> till anger and her Iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie made her speake too lowd to the Senate.</p>
               <p>But thine was loyall: so haue a world of others been. But <hi>Feare</hi> hath tript vp the heeles of some; Slander hath ouerthrowne others; and Malice hath brought a world to a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy'd Reputation.</p>
               <p>It is true (most men are of opinion) that whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is cold and ignorant,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:181116:56"/> must necessarily be subiect to inconstancie: and then women especially, because they are said to bee the Mistresses of all liuing things which are vnskilful. Whence there is drawne a Conclusion, That no woman, how excellent so euer, can draw vnto her Husband a settled and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine assurance of noble &amp; constant perseuerance.</p>
               <p>But this is a philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicke Disputation: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther needeth the losse to draw any argument of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace vpon the generall sexe. There are presidents enow both of their Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:181116:57"/> and Vices; their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stancies, and Inconstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; of the happy and lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable continuance of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble contracts, and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate breaches and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorces of ancient &amp; long coupled Matrimonies; there are Records suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, which speake of their vnyons and agreements: And there bee Tales in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance, to tell of their Brawles and Dissentions. We need not goe farre for examples: for euery <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gend</hi> is full of Yong mens dislikes, and Old mens iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousies; of Great mens al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations, and meane mens
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:181116:57"/> imitations. A world of married Beddes, carrie a world of vnmarried Thoughts; and howso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they walke coupled together in the streetes; yet is there (many times) as large a distance as was twixt <hi>Lazarus</hi> and <hi>Diues,</hi> betweene their affections: and howsoeuer the Sunne shine vpon the wedding day, yet there may bee many Gusts and Stormes ere the Vow come to the halfe way of performance. And therefore why shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest thou drowne thy selfe in teares, for that which is subiect to so short and
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:181116:58"/> so sudden an alteration?</p>
               <p>But thine was Good, was Chaste, was Modest, was Loyall, and would so haue continued euer if she had liued: shee was one that stood vpon her Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, not her Bloud: shee was not in loue with her selfe, but thee: shee was well brought vp, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer so much as once tain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with any obiect of ill example: she had no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements but thine to rule her; neither could she indure either Iewell or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell which had the least variation from her owne certaine estate and Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling:
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:181116:58"/> shee loued euer to keepe that house ouer her head, whose foundation was deep in the earth, and not bee hurried thorow the streetes in a Leather-Cart with foure wheeles, and taking a view of all men with as great libertie, as if shee gaz'd vpon her Husband: she respected a fit traine to guard her, not a throng or crowd to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire her. No, shee was innocent and free from all these dissolutions, and so free would haue liued con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, and dyed hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily.</p>
               <p>For this <hi>Hope</hi> or <hi>Assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:181116:59"/> (howsoeuer thou please to baptize it) thou art onely beholden to <hi>Death,</hi> and to no other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; he onely giues thee boldnes to maintaine it: for by his power (alone) is taken away all power that can either work in her Change, or in thee a Sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition. Shee must now be as good as thou canst con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue her: for (by the fauour of <hi>Death</hi>) shee hath ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowne all Detraction, all Temptation; and wilt thou repine &amp; murmure at this beholdingnesse? take heed lest it bring thee within the Lyst of Ingratitude.</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:181116:59"/>
               <p>To conclude, whether shee bee good, vertuous, chaste, modest or loyall, yet so mitigate and calme thy lamentation, that men may not (through the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of vnnecessary sorrow) question, whether thou weepest for thy wife, or some other diasaster: So remember thy selfe to be a Husband, that in no wise thou maist forget thou art a man: discretion in these affaires shewes princely and magnificent. A good mother, or a good sister, (lost by Death) are things vnrecouerable: and woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest thou imagine, that
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:181116:60"/> good wiues haue a greater priuiledge? O no, they are women; and so but acces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary goods, and reckene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> like the <hi>Vnicorne</hi> or the <hi>Phoenix,</hi> which though a man hunt after neuer so se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riously, yet shall he hardly▪ find aboue one in all his life time. Therefore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing found her, keepe her with thy best care, &amp; when thou shalt bee compelled by the necessitie of <hi>Destiny</hi> to forsake her, crowne her memorie with thy loue, and her tombe with a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate and modest lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Neither despaire of a second Choyce; for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:181116:60"/> haue bewailed the first, yet found the next of as large (if not a greater) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in vertue. They are gifts from aboue; vse thy best wisedome in election, and thy best care in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting ill example: and then, as noble Sir <hi>Philip Sidney</hi> writes,
<q>
                     <l>—Leaue the rest</l>
                     <l>To Fortune, Time, Wit,</l>
                     <l>and a Womans brest.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:181116:61"/>
            <head>The third Receipt.</head>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 11. </hi> A Cure against Contempt, and the Occasions: And first, of Contempt in generall.</head>
               <p>OF all the cruelties which Fortune can excercise vpon man, there is none appeareth with a more rough or deformed a countenance, nor breeds more affright to the soule, or torment to the mind, then that of <hi>Contempt:</hi> for when a man hath num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred all the miseries which can fall vpon him (in this
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:181116:61"/> life,) hee shall find none more Bitter or Gnawing, then that of <hi>Contempt:</hi> and thence it is said, that <hi>The greatest Affliction, is to suruiue Reputation; and the most infinit Folly, to put it in any Hazard of Losing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was noted for an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable modestie and wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in <hi>Ariosto,</hi> that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing been the onely Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, Schoole-fellow, play-mate, and Bed-fellow to <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth, yet after he came to the Popedom, neuer once attempted his fauour, or vrged him in any sute; but keeping still the countenance and grace
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:181116:62"/> of his eyes, contented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe with his owne for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and his owne Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes, lest by ascending any higher station, (and knowing the great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of better deseruers, which expected aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) hee might (by a sleight repulse) lose that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimation, which (howsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vnprofitable) the world yet held in reuerence.</p>
               <p>In Games and Maste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries (as in the old <hi>Olim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks,</hi> and other Trials of Honor) there is not one Prize or Crowne alone, but many; and he that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not winne the first, may
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:181116:62"/> hope the second, or the third: but in this Game or Goale of Vertue and faire life, hee that gets not the first, (which is Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) loses, or little profits by all the rest: for instant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Contempt</hi> takes him, and the golden chaine (which knit him and his good hopes together) is broke in pie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, and the whole course of his life after, is but falling and declining: but thou fearest to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned; and euen that Feare doth shake thee.</p>
               <p>It is true, that Feare is a malignant and hurtful pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, ingendred by A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:181116:63"/> and Doubt; which by a troublesome offence in the Soule, dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the blood from the heart, &amp; makes the whole Body faint and coward. It is a passion base and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate, yet furious and sudden: for when it strikes vpona yeelding Subiect, it strikes home, and the <hi>Life</hi> or <hi>Sences</hi> are euer in hazard. It is said, that one of the Dukes of <hi>Burgondy</hi> took his death (with feare) at the sight of the nine Worthies, (shewed him by a Magician.) And di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers (in our owne memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries) we haue knowne, that
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:181116:63"/> haue runne mad with the like apprehension: and though <hi>No man ought to feare, what must necessarily happen;</hi> yet daily wee see it is the fault of vncorrected Natures.</p>
               <p>Feare (saith <hi>Seneca</hi>) is without Loue, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of all high spirits to be forsaken: and yet for all this, and though Feare were much worse then any description can make it, there are alwaies two Feares allowable within vs; the one against <hi>Detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,</hi> the other against Gods iudgements; the first thou maist preuent
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:181116:64"/> by doing nothing which might make thee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible amongst men; and the latter thou mayest lessen, by carrying before God a cleare and vnbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened conscience.</p>
               <p>But thou fearest <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt;</hi> let the manner of thy life be honest, let not the corrupt conditions of Times breed inward Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postumes in thee; let not the estate of thy worldly affaires, draw thee from thy busines with God; let not <hi>Honors</hi> change thy ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Manner, nor great power conuert to greater couetousnes; and then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:181116:64"/> it, all good men will do thee reuerence; and for the contempt of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, it is an honorable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 12.</hi> A Cure against want of Strength, being an Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of Contempt.</head>
               <p>BVt now thou dost not feare <hi>Contempt,</hi> but art contemned; I pray thee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, from what ground springs that assurance? thou answerest me, From <hi>Want of Strength;</hi> thou art not powerfull or able of Body, but weake and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: Nature hath beene
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:181116:65"/> niggardly vnto thee, and not giuen thee force like other men.</p>
               <p>Doth this displease thee? art thou for this perplext and grieued? rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce and bee glad; for weaknesse is not lamenes; nor want of strength, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potence: euery man is not borne like <hi>Samson,</hi> to carry a Cities gates on his back: Some are borne for the Warres, some for the Court, and some for Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. Looke thou into the composition and Strength of thy mind; and if that promise thee a fruitful har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uest, thou hast strength a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:181116:65"/> enough to contend against many Armies. <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice</hi> is a Rampire of earth, <hi>Force</hi> but a wall of Stone; the first gathers strength by others fury; the latter fals assoone as it is shaken. <hi>Tully</hi> got as much honour with his wit, in preseruing <hi>Rome</hi> against the Conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie of <hi>Catiline,</hi> as <hi>Caesar</hi> had done in two and fiftie Battels, <hi>Marcellus</hi> in fortie, and <hi>Scipio</hi> in taking an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and two and fiftie Townes.</p>
               <p>But thou art subiect to Iniurie, euery one may tread vpon thee; thou must indure this mans scorne,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:181116:66"/> that mans slander, and the others buffets: thou must either feare all, or flatter all: thou must either bee a Moale &amp; liue alone with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out comfort, or else an Asse, to carry euery vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Burthen. But thou art deceiued, and in stead of sighing that thou art subiect to Iniury, thou shouldest reioyce, that (by reason of thy weaknesse) thou canst not doe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie. Doe we not see olde men walke in the Streetes without Guards, children passe by the mighty, and receiue Reuerence; and do wee not see (commonly)
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:181116:66"/> the most weake and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, keepe (as it were) in Chaines and Gyues, the most strong and valiant? The Lawes of all ciuil Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are thy sinewes; the Sword of the Magistrate, thy bones; and thine owne wisedome, hands to put one or both at any time in to executiō. Therfore sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the weaknesse of thy Body, with the strength of thy mind; learne wisdome, and pursue it, for it shalbe vnto thee a Tower against all aduersitie.</p>
               <p>A wise man (saith the best Morall master) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not receiue wrong, he hath
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:181116:67"/> so many Atmors of proof<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> against it, neither is he<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> subiect to the motions o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Anger, nor can by ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers malice bee mooued hee neuer intangles him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe with miseries, no<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> stands in need of strength or passion, either to pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>serue his Body, or perform his duty: hee is not ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious; for hee hath euer al<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Contentments in his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some, and he knowes both when, how, and to whom to doe those noble offices of friendship, which shal<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> still preserue him both from hate and disgraces▪ Take vnto thee then this
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:181116:67"/> companion, and thou nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest not feare to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with a twofold <hi>Goliah.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 13.</hi> A Cure against want of Greatnesse, being an Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of Contempt.</head>
               <p>NOw besides this weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of Body, thou wantest the Greatnesse and Dignity of place; thou hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest an vnder-fortune, and bearest a low Sayle, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as those which are great, and liue in admiration of the people: they sit high as on the tops of Turrets, and seeme to be compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with the Sunne, the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:181116:68"/> Moone, and all the rest of the celestiall Bodies.</p>
               <p>O foole! doe not tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thy selfe with these visions; for what (alas!) is all worldly Greatnesse? or whither doth it tend? exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all the great ones of the world, especially those who haue runne out the whole course of their liues in hunting after this <hi>Vapor</hi> or <hi>Shadow;</hi> they, whose thoughts anchoring whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon the earth, can haue no hopes, but such as are earthy: and these will tell thee, that Greatnesse is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but an huge Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of Vanitie; the assent
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:181116:68"/> whereto is sharpe and slip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie, the top shaking, and the downfall dreadfull: he that goes vp, finds difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in the passage, (for <hi>Feare</hi> is both his Guard and Guide) and he which descends, fals into an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bysse, where onely Shame cleaues to his memorie. It is a thing so vain and fraile, that when it seemes to gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster and sparkle like Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, euen then it vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes out of our sight, and either breakes like Glasse, or melts like yee, against the beames of Misfortune.</p>
               <p>Excellently is it sayd by that diuine Trumpet,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:181116:69"/>
                  <hi>Whatsoeuer is vnder heauen, is nothing but vanity, and that the world passeth away with his couetousnes.</hi> Which granted, O where is then the benefit of thy Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse? Bee wise then, and draw into thy considerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the earth is not thy dwelling house, but thine Inne; a place where onely thou lodgest for a night in thy iourney to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity: think that all Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, Delights, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentations which cluster about Greatnesse in this world, or adorne their Roomes, are but Motiues and Obligations to binde
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:181116:69"/> them to looke and prouide for much richer Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the world to come. For it is a thing ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surd in Reason, and irke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some to Nature, to goe foorth of a faire and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly House, and to enter for euer into a foule and loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some Cottage: This Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diocritie is the best Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; loue onely it, and be happie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:181116:70"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 14.</hi> A Cure against want of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, beeing an occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Contempt.</head>
               <p>IT may be, thou agreest with mee in this, that thou respectest not so much this vnreasonable Greatnesse, as thou doest a competent and fit pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment. But thou hast no aduancement in the State; thou hast no Sphere or range aboue the earth whereon thou treadest. Nay, thou seest many thine inferiours, men both of vnder deserts, and vnder
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:181116:70"/> qualities, who are aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and preferred many Stations beyond thee: thou seest them swimme in wealth, ruffle in authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, draw all eyes to gaze vpon them, and haue little petty Armies of their own dependants, to guard both before and behind them. This is offensiue to thee: this drawes griefe to thy Heart, and bitternesse to thy Soule, when thou comparest other mens glories and wealths with thine owne misfortunes; yet all this is but an enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Folly: for to iudge a man by his wealth, or his
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:181116:71"/> meanes, were to iudge an Horse by his Trappings, or an <hi>Asse</hi> by his burthen; and many times to attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute that to the Beast, which indeed belongeth onely to the Goddesse <hi>Isis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Was there euer any man so absurd as to enuy the Kings Exchequer, because it doth couer his Coyne, or can a man beare malice to a Rich mans Coffer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it hides his Bags? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it, such and no other are men of preferment in this age: for that man whom thou supposest to be the master of all this fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie and wealth, is but
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:181116:71"/> the poore Cap-case which carries it for a much better mans imploiment.</p>
               <p>I, but his preferments haue made him so infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rich, that howsoeuer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men fleece him, yet hee will still keepe a Staple sufficient both to cloath and make warme his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. If it bee so, then looke into his disposition, and tell me; Is he Couetous or Prodigall? If he be Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, thou canst not say he hath any thing; for that couetousnesse hath depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him of command, and made him a slaue to his Riches. Nay, it takes all
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:181116:72"/> thankefulnesse from him, and makes him guiltie of ingratitude. If he be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall, thou maist assure thy selfe he shall haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; for that channell will quickly conuay all to the common Ocean.</p>
               <p>I but hee shall haue his delights; he shall haue his contentment. No, nothing so: <hi>Preferments</hi> are euer inuironed with cares, with Feares, with Doubts, with Enuies. He which sits vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that tottering Stoole, sighes often, grieues deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, suspects alwayes, and is certaine neuer.</p>
               <p>I but yet for all this hee
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:181116:72"/> hath admiration in the world. The gazing multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude crowd about him: the better sort attend him: and the best in their prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stations seeme to loue him. This doubtlesse is true: and to knit vp or binde all these three together, thou maist (with as great a truth) affirme, that all in one doe but flatter him. Doe not <hi>Flyes</hi> follow Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; <hi>Wolues,</hi> Carrion; and <hi>Ants,</hi> Wheate? euen so doe these the man which sits in preferment. It is their owne prey they hunt, not his profit; their owne aduancement, not the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:181116:73"/> of his vertue; and if hee ascend, they can bee content to clamber after. But if hee descend, they seeke how to fixe fast their owne feete, and (many times with scorne) looke how and in what manner he falleth.</p>
               <p>To conclude: if thou wilt not haue thy vertue at any time to strike against this dangerous Rocke of <hi>Contempt,</hi> apply thy thoughts to noble and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest actions, according to the ranke and degree, wherein no counterfet, but true vertue hath plac't thee. Let the issue of one
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:181116:73"/> good designe, be the entry into another, make order both thy <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresse.</hi> Be Good, be Wise, bee Valiant, bee Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and then no doubt but thou shalt liue belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, preferred, and dye happy.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The fourth Receit.</head>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 15. </hi> Being a Cure against inward Paine, and the occasions: and first of paine in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</head>
               <p>HOwsoeuer I labour to recouer and cure
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:181116:74"/> the minde of these old rotting and increasing Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers; yet still thine infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction groweth new and more amply augmenteth, and now thou hast found a disease past helpe, past suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferance: thou art vexed with paine, inward Paine; paine of the Minde and Spirits; paine fixt vpon a part so tender and quicke of Sence, that the very anguish thereof spreads thorow the whole body, and thou art now Rackt, Tormented, and Broken vpon the wheele with all manner both of inward and outward vexations.</p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:181116:74"/>
               <p>It is true; I will allow thee in this case some little amazement, which for a poore minute may looke like Distraction: but I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not affoord thee so much <hi>Griefe,</hi> as to witnesse thy <hi>Paine</hi> to bee greater then thy wisedome: thou mayst take to thy selfe a liberty to change thy countenance, but not to alter thy Discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and thou maist (from some weakenesses) suffer Paine to extort from thee cryes and acclamations: But thou canst not from any soundnesse in Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, allow it any Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to disclose Secrets:
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:181116:75"/> thou maist so feele it, as to know a difference betwixt it, and perfect health: but not so entertaine it, as by an interposition it may draw any cloud or dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, betweene thee and thy vertue.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Stoicks</hi> held <hi>Paine</hi> onely to bee an opinion, and rather to abuse the minde by an imagination, then any reall or true fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: And questionlesse, to a noble and truely high Spirit, these flames or great lights of paine, are but like those of the <hi>Glowe-Wormes,</hi> which howsoeuer a weake Iudgement may
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:181116:75"/> shunne or feare to handle; yet a knowing experience boldly takes it vp, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces it either in his hand, or any other part, without sence of astonishment. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uola,</hi> when hee thrust his hand into the fire: <hi>Cleopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra,</hi> when she laid the <hi>Aspis</hi> to her Brest; the holy Martyrs, which sung and reioyst in the very height of all bodily afflictions, could neuer haue written <hi>Dulce quia Sponte,</hi> if their mindes had not carried them farre beyond the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of all mortall vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Aspasia,</hi> that smild vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Alexander</hi> whilst her
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:181116:76"/> childrens throats were in cutting: <hi>Hannibal</hi> that laught outright, when both <hi>Carthage</hi> and his own honor lay bleeding: and <hi>Croesus,</hi> that when hee had lost both the beautie of wealth, and the glory of a Kingdome, was able to teach <hi>Cyrus</hi> the happines of a contented retirement. All these are instances vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, to shew, how free e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery noble and worthy spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit should bee from these flegmaticke and weake ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensions of inward tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations.</p>
               <p>But thou answerest me, None will, none can resist
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:181116:76"/> the furie of Paine and Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and I reply, To say thou wilt not, is woman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish; to say thou canst not, is childish: for looke by how much man would (falsly) seeme to bee too weake to indure Paine, by double so much is Paine truly too weake to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand Reason; call that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer vp to assist thee, take thy direction from it, and not from vulgar and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude Opinion, and it will declare vnto thee, that all Paine whatsoeuer, is but like a Mole or spot vpon the cheek, which by a true application, may as well
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:181116:77"/> be taken for a Beauty, (as that on the cheeke of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>) as a deformitie, (as that on the face of <hi>Thersi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</hi>) It will tell thee, it is thy familiar and companion, not a Bugbeare or Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; a thing which thou broughtest with thee to the world; a thing thou canst not forsake in the world, and the onely thing that must infranchise and set thee free from all the miseries and perplexities of the world. It will tell thee, that Paine is nothing else, but an indulgent pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, to nourish thee vp in pious thoughts; a skilfull
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:181116:77"/> Master, to teach thee the happy art of Sufferance, a discreet Tutor to correct thy vices, and the onely Guide that can bee found to leade thee thorow the great Maze and Labyrinth of the vanities of this world, to the eternal ioyes of all true Felicitie.</p>
               <p>But O! this Paine is a tedious thing; it hath no meane or moderation in the working; it is an enemy to Meditation and good thoughts, and is indeed so farre from all peace and quietnesse, that it rather fils the head and heart with Frenzie and Despaire, then
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:181116:78"/> either with a fruitful Hope, or a feeding Charitie. but thou art deceiued, Paine is not tedious, but thou art effeminate; there is in it no manner of Terror, there is onely in thee a Resolution of Nicenesse: there is in it nothing to affright, there is only in thee a weake na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be afraid. Hunger is satisfied with bread and milke: <hi>Adam</hi> complained of no cold, when his body was cloath'd but with Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaues: Thirst hath need to search no further then the first fountaine; nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is there any other Paine, which finds not out
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:181116:78"/> a quick and a sudden Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy: Custome, Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie, and our owne opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are euer the false Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sengers, which make our afflictions more huge and monstrous then Nature created them: so that but correct the tendernesse of thine owne will, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently thou shalt finde Paine to vanish in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>I, but thou findest few which are able to follow these prescriptions; few or none can indure <hi>paine:</hi> then make thy selfe one of that little number. Lyons, Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles, euery noble Beast and
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:181116:79"/> Bird feed and flie alone: they are Sheepe, Geese, &amp; Dawes, that flocke and herd together. Be rather of Wisedoms little Band, then of Follies great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. But thou wilt answer me, That the weaknesse of thy nature, makes thy Wil a slaue to thy Torment: come, neither abuse nor defame Nature; for shee hath created al men strong and valiant: it is Custome and Education which make Cowards; liue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy creation: suffer nor the seueritie of <hi>Rule,</hi> and other mens Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, to infect thee, and
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:181116:79"/> then beleeue it, these fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, these affrights, these tremblings at Paine will neuer come neere thee: thou shalt then need nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to labour thy wits for auoyding it, nor tire thy limbes in flying away from it: thou shalt then know, that to runne away from <hi>Paine,</hi> is to meet <hi>Paine;</hi> and that the more thou striuest to shake it off, the more it cleaues vnto thee, and more strong are the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracements. It is an insul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting enemy, where it finds a fearefull opponent; and therefore face it, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face it; be as carelesse of its
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:181116:80"/> power, as others are care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to make it powerfull, and like a fearefull Hare, it will flie from thy presence: for as nothing, like vnto Nicenesse feeds it, so no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, like <hi>Contempt,</hi> is able to abate or destroy it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 16.</hi> A Cure against Sorrow, Cares, &amp;c. being an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of Paine.</head>
               <p>AFter all the warre and contentiō which thou hast held against the mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of these Misfortunes, thou yet feelest another, which is more bitter and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:181116:80"/> vnpleasant, then any that haue gone before it, and that is <hi>Sorrow,</hi> Griefe, or heauinesse of heart, which according to the most ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall receiued opinion, is nothing else, but <hi>A Passion of the Soule, which ariseth from a discontent shee recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth from obiects contrary to her inclination, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent themselues vnto the Senses, and afflict them:</hi> and with this Sorrow, or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinesse of heart, thou art now tormented. But let it not deceiue thy iudgment; examin the cause well, and try, if it be worthy of thine anguish: for there are two
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:181116:81"/> sorts of Sorrowes, a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and a lesse: one that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in the Body, another that liueth in the Minde.</p>
               <p>That <hi>sorrow</hi> which liueth in the Body, and is both moued, and moueth the same, is not so powerfull and terrible, as the other: and therefore are Intituled by the name of Slight <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes,</hi> or Slight Cares; which if they get any Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion or Rule ouer thee, chide thy weake nature which entertain'd them: and with a braue suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance make the world know that the burthen is light and easie: call <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi>
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:181116:81"/> vnto thee, shee is euer a ready and an easie ghest to a wiseman: shee craues not much diligence to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend her: nor is at any time so troublesome, but that shee may with much pleasantnesse bee suppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: take her counsell, she will teach thee how to suffer, how to doe: she will tell thee how to beare all things, both <hi>Pro, A</hi> and <hi>Propter,</hi> both for thy selfe and others, of thy selfe and others, and because of thy selfe and others: she hath euer cold water enough to quench the hottest flames that Sorrow can kindle,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:181116:82"/> and shee will tell thee that it is a wretched victory which ouercomes the Soule, and makes it a slaue to inward vexation.</p>
               <p>Sorrow is neither profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to thy selfe, nor to them for whom thou dost sorrow: it is absurd to sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for things which are past help, and meere chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dishnesse to spend our griefe vpon a neglecting Subiect, that we must sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for, (as death) neuer sorrows for vs againe; and then what greater foolish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse then thus to spend la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation? Againe, looke by how much thou art
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:181116:82"/> greater either in Place, Authoritie, Renowne, or Vertue: by so much the less thou shouldest expresse grief for any worldly mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture: for vnreasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sorrow is a true Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of Cowardize: and where that weaknes grows, the fruit it brings forth, is onely Scorne, and dis-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</p>
               <p>But thy Sorrow is no slight Sorrow; it hath a deepe Roote, and a strong Foundation; it is fixed to thy Heart, and hath taken vp thy Minde for a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall habitation: if it be so, it is thy greater glory to
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:181116:83"/> subdue it; it is pleasant to hunt Deere; but Princely to conquer Lyons. Take vnto thy selfe the exercise of Noble and worthy things, and beleeue it, thou shalt finde that sorrow will quickly vanish. Nailes are driuen out by Nailes, and the fury of Sorrow is easily expell'd with the strength of Wisedome. Do but take into thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration the miserable effects which spring from sorrow: as first, the quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Spirit (making it vncapable either to search or finde out truth) the solitarinesse of the life
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:181116:83"/> (accounting all societie irkesome) the hating of the light (as if the Sunne did manifest euery priuate imagination,) the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>application of all manner of comforts and the disea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses; nay, the deaths which succeed these inward af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and no doubt but thou wilt quickly bee wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of so insolent and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blesome a neighbour: Therefore to merit quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, truely, soundly, be sure to lessen and abate the strength of the opinion which thou holdest in it: for indeed Sorrow is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else but meerely opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion:
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:181116:84"/> which when at any time thou shalt either blunt with Reason, or bend with Discourse &amp; inward Disputation; suddenly thou shalt see all his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish depart, and Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome filling vp the room, will make all things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare pleasant and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some. And to conclude, howsoeuer <hi>Time</hi> may bee allowed for a Physicion in this case; yet it is <hi>Reason</hi> only, which must make the cure perfect.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:181116:84"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>